AI翻译  以官方英字为准
网飞出品
NETFLIX PRESENTS
安达卢西亚 1936年
Andalusia, 1936
突袭 - 入侵 突然袭击
raid - incursion, sudden attack,
对敌人的快速突袭造成混乱
rapid raid party against the enemy to cause turmoil
所有人现在行动
Everyone move now
快 这边走
Quick! This way
快点 起来 快
Come on, get up, quick!
快点 起来
Come on, get up!
快点
Quick now!
你想要什么?
What do you want?
这里没有人
There's no one here
伊吉尼奥 快
Higinio, quick
快 快
Quick, quick!
快
Quick!
马上开门 -去找他
Open now! - Go find him
在邻居家 -来吧 也检查那扇门
In the neighbor's house. - Come on, check that door, too!
开门
Open!
Open up!
早上好
Good morning
让开 别动
Out of the way. Don't move
检查后面
Check the back
我能帮忙吗？-扣上扣子
Can I help? - Button it
也检查院子 -我丈夫昨晚走了
Check the courtyard too. - My husband left last night
这里没人 -闭嘴
There's nobody here. - Shut up
没有人 -看到了吗？我说的话
There's nobody. - See? What I said
好了 名单上的下一个
All right, next ones on the list
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
什么事？
What is it?
听着 我需要逃跑
Listen, I need to make a run for it
他们会洗劫一切
They'll ransack everything
你要去哪里？-山还是安全的地方
Where will you go? - The mountains or somewhere safe
我可以和你一起去吗？-不 我会回来找你的
Shall I go with you? - No, I'll come back for you
坚持住 坚持住 坚持住
Hang on, hang on, hang on
拿着这个
Take this
这是干什么用的？
What's it for?
所以你可以戴着它 发生
So you can wear it. Go on
快 在这里
Quick! Over here!
在这里
Over here!
是伊吉尼奥
It's Higinio!
停下 -停下
Stop! - Stop!
移开它
Move it
这些是最后一批了 我们结束了 是吧？
These are the last ones and we're done, huh?
快点 动起来 到达
Come on, move it. Get in
别动
Don't move!
快点 快点
Get a move on, quick!
来吧 前进
Come on! Get a move on!
闭嘴
Shut up!
我一个字也不想听
I don't want to hear a word!
来吧 快点 快点
Come on! Get a move on, quick!
别说话 嗯？
No talking, huh?
那里发生了什么？
What's going on in there?
来吧 出来吧
Come on, out you come!
动起来 -你要带他们去哪里？
Move it. - Where are you taking them?
闭嘴 -离开她
Shut up! - Leave her!
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
安静 不许动
Quiet! Nobody move!
来吧 快走 -所有人都呆在原地
Come on! Move! - Everyone stay put!
安静 -走 走 走
Quiet! - Go, go, go!
搞什么鬼？坐下 -拜托
What the hell? Sit down. - Please
你到底在干吗-拜托
What the hell are you doing? - Please
我求你了 -回你的地方去
I'm begging you. - Go back to your place!
滚开
Get off!
其中一个逃走了 停下
One of them got away! Stop!
停下 停下 停下
Stop, stop, stop!
停下
Stop!
站住
Halt!
他往那边跑了
He ran that way!
费德 我是伊吉尼奥
Fede, it's Higinio
伊吉尼奥
Higinio
你真的吓了我们一跳
You gave us a real fright
这是怎么回事？
What's going on here?
这是怎么回事？-你期待什么？
What's going on? - What did you expect?
我可以预见这一切疯狂的到来
I could see all this madness coming
我看得出来 -什么？
I could see it. - What?
我告诉你多少次了？子弹解决不了这个问题
How many times did I tell you? Bullets won't solve this.
神父不能被触摸
Priests can't be touched
地主是不可触摸的
Landowners can't be touched
子弹解决不了问题 我告诉你一千遍了
Bullets won't solve it. I told you a thousand times
我没有下令杀人
I didn't order any killings
但是你的人做到了 你支持他们
But your people did. You support them
到处乱射你的嘴
Shooting your mouth off about
不得不杀人 现在看看我们有什么
having to kill, and now look what we have
这太疯狂了
This is complete madness
让我们尽量安静下来
Let's try to be quiet down here
想来根烟吗？
Fancy a cigarette?
一支烟 嗯？一支香烟
A cigarette, huh? A cigarette
有助于缓和一些事情
Help soothe things a bit
这是达米安 我的表弟
This is Damián, my cousin
他昨晚到达 几天前在卡蒙纳逃脱了一次突袭
He arrived last night, escaped a raid a few days ago in Carmona
我认识你
I know you
大约一年前我在一次会议上见过你
I saw you at a meeting about a year ago
我来自支持小组
I was from the support group
是的 你的脸看起来很面熟
Yeah, your face looks familiar
你为我们做了很多
You did a lot for us
如果你愿意 来和我们一起战斗
Come and fight with us if you want
我该拿罗莎怎么办？
What do I do about Rosa?
我得去接她
I have to fetch her
你要回村子？
You're going back to the village?
那是进入狮子的洞穴
That's going into the lion's den
她被报道了吗？
Has she been reported?
一点也不
Not at all
罗莎不从政 只有我
Rosa doesn't get into politics, just me
那她会没事的
She'll be all right, then
他们不久前结婚了
They got married not long ago
正确
Right
看看会发生什么？
See what happens?
很容易认出新婚夫妇
It's easy to spot a newly-wed
这就是我的想法
That's what I think
够了 对吧？
It's enough, right?
走吧
Let's go
贡萨洛
Gonzalo!
贡萨洛 -这是什么？
Gonzalo. - What is it?
进来
Come in
来
Coming
你整晚都呆在外面还是什么？
Are you staying out all night or what?
约肯来了
Joaquín is coming
你为什么和这些人在一起？
Why are you with these people?
那是我的事
That's my business
不要惹麻烦
Don't get into trouble
你什么意思？
What trouble do you mean?
好吧 吃点晚饭
All right, have some dinner
我不想吃晚饭
I don't want dinner
我不觉得饿
I don't feel hungry
亲爱的上帝 伊吉尼奥
Dear God, Higinio
发生什么事了？
What happened?
我们得走了
We have to go
发生什么事了？
What happened?
我们必须拿走所有的钱
We have to take all the money there is
去山里
And head for the mountains
在天亮之前
before it gets light
你的腿怎么了？
What happened to your leg?
发生什么事了？
What happened?
别动
Don't move
上帝 你看到你的腿了吗？
God, have you seen the state of your leg?
子弹还在里面
The bullet is still in there
罗莎 -什么？
Rosa. - What?
如果他们抓到我 我就死定了
If they catch me, I'm dead
听着 你看到你的腿了吗？
Listen, have you seen the state of your leg?
你要去哪里？
Where will you go?
走吧 -不 你听我说
Let's go. - No, you listen to me
他们遍布全村
They're all over the village
睡觉吧 我会在这里呆一会儿
Go to bed. I'll stay here a while
开始
Come on
伊吉尼奥
Higinio,
看着我
look at me
你为什么要打那个洞？
Why did you make that hole?
贡萨洛四处张望 什么也没发现
Gonzalo was looking around there and didn't spot a thing
为什么不进去 我们可以治疗你的伤口
Why not get in there, we can treat your wound,
然后我们离开 好吗？
and then we leave. Okay?
请
Please
开始
Come on
这就是方法
That's the way
开始
Come on
隐藏——将某人或某物转移到一个安全的地点或地方
hide - to move somebody or something to a safe location or place
你在做什么?-拿下他们
What are you doing? - Taking them down
他们说所有的窗帘都要放下来
They’ve said that all the curtains have to come down!
没有 但是...你搜查了房子 现在又搜查了窗帘
No, but... You searched the house, and now the curtains
我会把它们拿下来 就这样
I'll take them down and that's it
看到了吗？问题解决了
See? Problem solved
贡萨洛 听我说
Gonzalo, listen to me a minute
等一下 停一下 你是知道的
Just a second, stop a minute. You know
也许伊吉尼奥没有用正确的方式做好每一件事
that maybe Higinio didn't do everything the right way,
但是他从不伤害任何人 他不应该在名单上
but he never hurt anyone, he shouldn't be on a list
你了解我们
You know us
嗯 首先他必须出现 然后我们会看到
Well, first he has to turn up, then we'll see
但是我的意思是你可以说这是一个错误
But I mean that you could say it was a mistake,
把他的名字从名单上去掉 -一个错误？
and take his name off the list. - A mistake?
他烧了不该烧的东西 犯了错误 是吗？
He made the mistake when he burnt down what he shouldn't, huh?
烧了什么？
Burnt what?
什么？
What?
巴尔塞纳尔修道院
Barcenillas hermitage,
属于卡梅尔修女 圣斐理伯·奈里 他没说吗？
belongs to the Carmelite nuns, St. Philip Neri, did he not say?
那不是真的 -不是吗？
That isn't true. - Didn't he?
这不是真的 -没有？
It's not true. - No?
他可能有自己的想法 但他不暴力
He may have his ideas, but he's not violent
当他们杀了贡萨洛的兄弟时 他做了什么？
What did he do when they killed Gonzalo's brother?
他什么也没做
He did nothing
对 他什么也没做 什么也没说 他是议员
Right, he didn't do or say anything, and he was a councillor
伊莎贝尔 回家吧
Isabel, go home
不不不我想让她知道
No, no, no. I want her to know
现在她在乞求 但我想让她知道你有多孤独
Now she's begging, but I want her to know how alone you felt
拜托 伊莎贝尔
Please, Isabel
别装无辜 好吗？不要这样做
Don't act the innocent, all right? Don't do it
我们被关了起来 害怕如果我们出去他们会有所行动
We've been locked up afraid they'd do something if we went out
你们都不在乎
And you lot didn't care
如果这些人没来 我丈夫会是下一个
If these people hadn't come, my husband would have been next
好了 够了 得了
Okay, that's enough. Stop it
别管它 走吧 回家
Just stay out of it. Go on, go home
回家吧 女人
Go home, woman
听我说 贡萨洛
Listen to me, Gonzalo
你知道 你很清楚
You know, you know full well,
我们对你哥哥有多难过
how sad we are about your brother
我们一发现 伊吉尼奥就亲自去告诉你了
As soon as we found out, Higinio himself went to tell you that
现在你明白我为什么要做什么了吗？
Now do you understand why I have to do something?
我求你了
I'm begging you please
你应该对你丈夫说的
You should have said that to your husband
恳求他
Begged him
你应该求他的 对吗？
You should have begged him, right?
来吧 贡萨洛
Come on, Gonzalo
不要拉窗帘 -我要带走他们
Don't take the curtains. - I'm taking them
不要 它们是我的 把窗帘给我
Don't, they're mine. Give me the curtains!
把他们交出来
Hand them over
它们是我的 给我
They're mine, give them to me!
别拿窗帘 贡萨洛
Don't take the curtains, Gonzalo
什么事？搜查雷麦黛丝的房子
What is it? Searching Remedios's house.
“金发男”
”The blond guy”,
和“寨子男”逃走了
and “the stockade guy” got away
你在那里做什么？
What are you doing there?
外面发生了什么？
What's going on outside?
不 这不是重点 我说了什么？
No, that isn't the point. What did I say?
你和谁谈过了吗？
Did you talk to anyone?
帮我个忙 进去吧 -你和谁谈过了吗？
Do me a favour and get in there. - Did you talk to anyone?
阿曼多改变了立场
Armando has switched sides
双胞胎 对吗？
The twin, right?
不 诺加莱斯
No, Nogales
诺加莱斯？
Nogales?
我现在谁都不相信
I don't trust anyone now
贡萨洛正在分发一份名单
Gonzalo is giving out a list of names
没有什么比愤怒的白痴更糟糕的了
There's nothing worse than an angry idiot
黄油在他嘴里不会融化 现在看看他在胡说八道
Butter wouldn't melt in his mouth, now look at him blabbing
他的问题是他害怕
The trouble with him is that he's scared
害怕什么？
Scared of what?
我不知道
I don't know
我们会回来的
That we'll come back
你涂药膏了吗？
Did you put on the ointment?
我完全忘记了药膏
I forgot all about the ointment
小心 小心
Careful, careful
疼吗？
Does it hurt?
我可以忍受
I can put up with it
天啊 你真臭
God, you really stink
你说我臭是什么意思？-这个
What do you mean I stink? - This
怎么了？它有我的味道
What's wrong? It smells of me
自从你进去后就没换过
You haven't changed it since you got in there
我为什么要换衬衫？
Why would I change shirts?
我的背真的很痛
My back is really hurting.
我已经能走路了
I can already walk
伊吉尼奥
Higinio
什么？
What?
下周的计划是不可能的
What was planed for the next week is going to be impossible
你怎么能这么说？
How can you say that?
他们逮捕了要带我们去葡萄牙的人
They arrested the man who was going to get us to Portugal
那不可能 罗莎 那不可能
That can't be, Rosa, that can't be
那不可能 -没关系 我会想办法的
That can't be. - It's all right, I'll find a way
我们现在必须离开 我们必须冒这个险
We have to leave now. We have to risk it
我们不能再等了
We can't wait any longer
现在是时候了
Now is the time
我们现在必须离开 -看在上帝的份上
We must leave now. - For God's sake
放轻松 我会找到办法的
Take it easy, I'll find a way
逮捕——法律权威对自由的暂时丧失
arrest - temporary loss of freedom by authority of law
如果你什么都不知道 为什么这么紧张？
If you don't know anything, why so nervous?
我不知道
I don't know
如果你这么晚来我家 你会有什么期待？
What do you expect if you come to my house this late?
你没听说过他 甚至没从别人那里听说过？
You didn't hear about him, not even from someone else?
不 我已经说过了 他走了 这是我最后一次听到
No, I already said I didn't. He left and that was the last I heard
那你为什么这么想把他从名单上抹去？
Then why are you so desperate to have him wiped off the list?
你还没喝够吗？
Haven't you already had enough?
我什么都不知道
I don't know anything
他离开时你说了什么？
What did you say when he left?
没什么 我甚至不能说再见
Nothing, I couldn't even say goodbye
你怎么知道他什么时候离开的？
So how did you know what time he left?
时间 我
The time, I
他早上离开了 但不知道什么时候
He left in the morning, but I don't know at what time
前几天他们看见你在洗一个男人的衬衫
They saw you washing a man's shirt the other day
不要装傻
Don't act stupid
这里没有什么不被注意的
Nothing goes unnoticed here
还是不是你丈夫的？
Or wasn't it your husband's?
是的 它是...这是我丈夫的 但是
Yes, it is... It was my husband's, but
他走后一周 我发现它很脏 所以我就把它洗了
I found it a week after he left, it was dirty so I washed it
你的邻居说你总是开着前门
Your neighbors say you always kept the front door open,
现在它几乎总是关着
now it's almost always shut
正是我所需要的
Just what I needed
别哭了
Quit crying
我说别哭了 好吗？
I said quit crying, okay?
如果你现在不合作 我们有命令要执行
If you don't collaborate now, we have orders to carry out
你瞧...我真的什么都不知道
You see... I really don't know anything
几个问题
A couple of questions
不不不还有问题吗？但是我已经告诉你了
No, no, no, more questions? But I already told you
不求你了 -不要让它变得更难
No, please! - Don't make it more difficult
请不要这样做
Please don't do this!
我什么都不知道 也不知道他在哪里 看在上帝的份上 请不要
I don't know anything or where he is. For God's sake, please don't!
来吧 -我想留在这里
Come on now. - I want to stay here!
我告诉你我什么都不知道
I'm telling you that I don't know anything!
请
Please
他不在吗？
Is he not here?
看起来是这样
Looks that way
我告诉你 我听到噪音 嗯？
I tell you, I hear noises, huh?
你检查过了吗？-哪里？
Did you check there? - Where?
在那里
There
罐子在哪里
Where the jars are
看看里面
Have a look inside
它是空的
It's empty
看起来这里面有点油
Looks like there's a bit of oil in this one
确定吗？
Sure?
这里没人 -没什么？
No one here. - Nothing?
滚开
Scram!
滚开 那不是给你的
Scram, that isn't for you!
给我
Give it to me!
罗莎
Rosa
他们对你做了什么？
What did they do to you?
发生什么事了？
What happened?
你怎么了？
What happened to you?
他们告诉我他们抓到你了
They told me that they'd caught you
我一句话也没说
I didn't say a word
结束了 让他们抓住我
It's over. Let them just catch me
如果我连你都照顾不了 为什么我会在这里？
Why am I here if I can't even take care of you?
来这里
Come here
伊吉尼奥
Higinio
什么？
What?
他们告诉我 我必须每天去军营报到
They told me I have to report to the barracks every day
和
And
他们让我把门开着
They've made me leave the front door open
没关系
It's all right
It's fine
答应我 如果我不在 你不会出来
Promise me you won't come out if I'm not here
答应我
Promise me
发誓
Swear on it
我发誓
I swear
你想象大海是什么样子的？
What do you imagine the sea looks like?
我不知道
I don't know
贡萨洛来了
Gonzalo is coming.
我想象当阳光猛烈照射下来时
I imagine that when the sunlight is shining down hard
我想你
I miss you.
它一定像夏天的乡村
it must be like the countryside in summer
太阳与地平线融为一体
and the sun merges with the horizon
就像那样 但是有水
Like that, but with water
先别走
Don't go yet.
真遗憾
What a pity
我爱你
I love you.
我们应该让你父亲支付蜜月费用
We should have let your father pay for the honeymoon
当我们用挣来的钱去做的时候 我们会更享受它
We'll enjoy it more when we do it with the money we earn
你知道今天是星期几吗？
Do you know what day today is?
当然 周年快乐
Of course, happy anniversary.
罗莎
Rosa
以后别忘了适当搅拌骨灰
Don't forget to stir the ashes properly later
好
All right
你已经告诉我三次了
You told me three times already
我向你要的书呢？
What about the books I asked you for?
我不能被看到带着关于政治的书
I can't be seen bringing books on politics
还有那些...很明显他们不适合我
and things that... It's obvious they're not for me
孩子们 过来 你好 -你好
Kids, come here. Hello. - Hello
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
帮我个忙 进去吧
Do me a favour and get in there
你能进去吗？
Can you please get in there?
我在听人们在说什么
I'm listening to what people are saying
我透过窗户偷看的时候看见了佩罗
I saw Pero when I was peeking through the window
他不是站在民族主义阵营的前线吗？
Wasn't he on the front with the Nationalist faction?
要么他有一个双胞胎兄弟 要么他在外面庆祝胜利
Either he has a twin brother or he's out there celebrating the victory
罗莎
Rosa
结束了吗？
Is it over?
你为什么不告诉我？
So why don't you tell me?
因为还没有结束
Because it isn't over
他们处决了阿里纳斯
They executed Arenas
恩里克 安德烈斯 奎约
And Enrique, Andrés, Quijo
他们杀了所有被抓的议员
They killed all the councillors that they caught
他们已经悬赏捉拿你
They've put out a reward for your capture
我听说他们出价6万比塞塔
I heard they're offering 60,000 pesetas
我做了什么才值那么多钱？
What have I done to be worth that much?
我不知道 他们说你做了可怕的事情
I don't know, they're saying you did terrible things
谁说的？-每个人
Who's saying that? - Everyone
那些从前面回来的人
Those coming back from the front
他们责怪你们中没有回来的人
they are blaming those of you who didn't come back
所以 还没有结束
So, it isn't over
危险——可能发生坏事的风险或迫在眉睫的可能性
danger - risk or imminent possibility that something bad may occur
你觉得她知道些什么吗？
Think she knows something?
我也这么认为她在隐瞒什么
I think so. She's hiding something
我们必须审问她 尽我们所能
We have to interrogate her, get as much as we can
在这里审问她 -我不同意
Interrogate her right here. - I don't agree
我们带她一起去吧 审问她和其他什么
Let's take her with us. Interrogate her and whatever else
不 不可能 听我说
No, no way. Listen to me
我们照我说的做 在这里审问她
We do as I say, interrogate her here
你在大喊大叫
You're shouting
会再发生的 等着瞧吧
It'll happen again, just wait and see
自从战争结束后 他变得更加着迷
Since the war ended he's become even more obsessed
罗莎
Rosa!
贡萨洛 我是伊吉尼奥 我的岳父 我们在吃饭 好吗？
Gonzalo, It’s Higinio, my father-in-law. We are having dinner, okay?
行
Okay
每天都一样
Same thing every day
那么 伊吉尼奥没事吧？
So, is Higinio all right?
他没事
He's all right
但是这越来越让人无法忍受了
But this is getting unbearable
他开始在睡梦中大喊大叫
He's beginning to shout in his sleep
前几天他们把这个地方翻了个底朝天
They turned the place upside down the other day
我不知道他们怎么没找到他
I don't know how they didn't find him
你是说他在这里？
You mean he's here?
他在那里
He's there
罐子下面
Under the jars
他藏在里面
He's hiding inside there
亲爱的上帝
Dear God
他在那里已经三年了
He's been there three years
几乎
Pretty much
如果你愿意 把架子上的盘子拿来 说几句话
If you want, fetch the plates on the shelf and have a word
请帮我把那些盘子拿来
Do me a favour and fetch me those plates, please
父亲
Father
从架子上拿些东西 任何东西
Pick something off the shelf, anything
但是你为什么不跟我说点什么？
But why didn't you say anything to me?
我们认为最好不要告诉任何人
We thought it was best not to tell anyone
父亲 我需要你的帮助
Father, I need your help
你想要什么都行
Whatever you want
餐具柜所在的墙
The wall where the sideboard is
我需要你建一堵假墙
I need you to build a false wall,
然后在餐具柜后面挖一个洞
and then make a hole behind the sideboard
你想藏在那里吗？
You want to hide in there?
是
Yes
你的房子更安全
Your house is safer
罗莎会给你看计划
Rosa will show you the plans
你建墙越快越好
The sooner you build the wall, the better
一旦准备好了 伊吉尼奥就会去那里
As soon as it's ready, Higinio will go there
你呢？
What about you?
i...如果你不介意的话
I... If you don't mind,
我会和你一起住
I'd move in with you
如果人们问 我们会告诉他们钱很紧
If people ask, we tell them that money is really tight and
这样我就可以管理你已故妻子的工作室
that way I can take charge of your deceased wife's workshop
快
Quick
记得用茴香和熏衣草来清理这个洞以去除气味
Remember to clean the hole with anise and lavender to get rid of the smell
行
Okay
不 等等 等等 让我看看
No, hang on. Wait. Let's see
好了
Done
就这样
That's it
准备
Ready
你会做得很好的 又好又快
You'll do a good job. Nice and quick
走吧 你走吧
Go on, off you go
罗莎
Rosa
趁大家都在游行的时候 现在就做 快点
Do it now while everyone is at the procession, hurry
什么事？
What is it?
我不能 -是的 你可以
I can't. - Yes you can
什么意思?听我说
What do you mean? Listen to me
如果你留下来 他们会抓住你的
If you stay, they'll catch you
你现在必须走了
You have to go now
你当然可以 你为什么不呢？
Of course you can. Why wouldn't you?
你能做到的
You can do it
我不会丢下你不管的
I won't leave you alone
你会做得很好的 好吗？
You'll do a great job, okay?
开始
Come on
西班牙万岁
REDS OUT LONG LIVE SPAIN
匆忙
Hurry
快点 我们要迟到了
Come on, we'll be late
移动它
Move it
你在找什么吗 夫人？
Are you looking for something, madam?
不好意思
Excuse me!
站住 这是国民警卫队
Halt, this is the Civil Guard!
住手 否则我开枪了
Stop or I'll shoot!
这是国民警卫队
This is the Civil Guard!
进来
Come in
脱下那些衣服
Take off those clothes
他们全部
All of them
你为什么花了这么长时间？
Why did you take so long?
我迷路了
I got lost
在你的村子里？-是的
In your village? - Yes
里面有一个洗脸盆可以自己洗
There's a basin in there to wash yourself
快点 快点
Come on, hurry up
儿子
Son
你还好吗？
Are you all right?
是
Yes
你需要什么吗？
Do you need anything?
不
No
如果你需要什么...-安静
If you need anything... - Silence!
沉默
Silence
这正是我需要的
That's what I need
将人或动物放在他们不能离开的地方
enclose - put a person or an animal in a place they cannot leave
我在兵营旁边的广场上看见了他
I saw him in the square, next to the barracks
他难过得无法和儿子说再见
So sad he couldn't say goodbye to his son
现在他离开了这个世界 再也不能
Now he's left this world and won't be able to
让我们上路吧
Let's be on our way
1944年2月8日
FEBRUARY 8th, 1944
我有三袋土 你知道吗？
I have three sacks of dirt, you know?
明天给我
Give them to me tomorrow
我估计大约一年后
I reckon that in about a year or so
我会一直挖到树林
I'll have dug the hole as far as the grove
如果发生了什么
And if anything happens
伊吉尼奥 我想要个孩子
Higinio, I want a baby
别再这样了 罗莎
Not this again, Rosa
我们不是说过盟军何时赢得战争吗？
Didn't we say when the allies won the war?
那会是什么时候？他们什么时候会赢？
And when will that be? When will they win?
当我不能再有孩子的时候？
When I can't have children anymore?
当我的肚子开始露出来时 我会去格拉纳达
When my belly starts showing, I'll go to Granada
那我就说这是我必须照顾的侄子
Then I'll say it's a nephew I have to take care of
同时 我如何生存？
Meanwhile, how do I survive?
我会给你留下食物和你需要的任何东西
I'll leave you food and whatever else you need
你能听到自己吗？
Can you hear yourself?
你没意识到这很荒谬而且很危险吗？
Don't you realise it's absurd and really dangerous?
你知道他们会杀了你、我和孩子吗？
Do you realise they could kill you, me and the baby?
你知道会发生什么吗？
Do you realise what might happen?
让我们开动脑筋 是拯救的时候了
Let's use our heads. Is the time to save
我可以帮你织补 做褶边...拜托 罗莎
I can lend you a hand darning, doing hems... Please, Rosa
让我们用我们的头脑
Let's use our heads
让我们给盟友一些时间
Let's give the allies some time
今天 1944年6月6日
Today, 6 June 1944,
盟军已经开始让超过15万名士兵登陆
the allies have started disembarking over 150,000 troops
由艾森豪威尔将军率领的盟军
Led by General Eisenhower, allied troops
战胜了元帅·隆美尔开发的防御系统
have overcome the defences developed by Field Marshal Rommel
英美空军司令部
British and US command of the air
是手术成功的关键
were key to the success of the operation
盟军飞机摧毁了塞纳河和卢瓦尔河上的桥梁
Allied aircraft have destroyed bridges over the Seine and the Loire
成功的登陆使盟军快速前进
The successful landing has enabled allied troops to quickly advance
走向法国的心脏
towards the heart of France
伸出你的手臂
Hold your arms out
好的
Great
看起来不错吧 -是的 你现在会穿它吗？
Looks good, huh? - Yes. Will you wear it now?
我会像那样扣上扣子
I'll button it up like that
这
This
周四之前我会有另一个
I'll have the other one by Thursday
好吗？
Okay?
好的
Great
好
All right
你是艺术家罗莎
You're an artist Rosa
现在你可以告诉人们我不只是缝制服 我修补各种
Now you can tell people I don't just sew uniforms. I mend all sorts
价格也不错
And for a good price, too
他们可以看到最漂亮的女裁缝
And they get to see the prettiest seamstress
你是个圆滑的人 我也向你收费
You're a smooth one. I'm charging you the same
我只是作为一个艺术爱好者说的
I'm just saying it as an art lover
我的靴子在哪里？
Where are my boots?
哦 是的
Oh, yes
停止
Stop
不 停下
No, stop
现在不行 停下
Not now, stop
我得去月经了 停下
I have to get my period, stop
一个来自科尔多瓦的有趣女孩
A fun girl from Córdoba
这让我爱上了她
It's what made me fall in love with her
那时情况不同
Things were different then
因为几个月来
Because for a few months now,
她看起来总是很悲伤
she always looks sad
好像她对什么都不感兴趣
Like she's not excited about anything
现在她所做的就是吃东西
Now all she does is eat
她只吃东西 从不出门
All she does is eat, never leaves the house
我说 卡门 让我们去节日 让你自己漂亮
I say, Carmen, let's go to the festival, make yourself pretty
让我们穿上色彩鲜艳的衣服...
A colourful dress, let's...
充分利用节日 -像以前一样
Make the most of the festival. - Like before
她觉得不能胜任
She doesn't feel up to it
她现在不一样了
She's not the same now
可怜的东西
Poor thing
也许我匆忙结婚了
Maybe I rushed into getting married
别这么说 罗德里戈
Don't say that, Rodrigo
这些事情需要时间 需要习惯
These things take time, they take getting used to
为什么是那张脸？
Why that face?
什么脸？
What face?
那张脸
That face
什么脸？
What face?
你笑了 不是吗？
You smiled, didn't you?
看到我充满疑虑 你觉得好笑吗？
Do you find it funny to see me full of doubts?
不 反过来
No, it's the other way around
我为你们俩感到难过
I feel sad for both of you
不管怎样 我不知道
Anyway, I don't know
这里还有一个洞
There's another hole here, too
又一个？-是的
Another one? - Yes
我没见过那个
I hadn't seen that one
那是星期天的
That's from Sunday
我会帮你修好的 我会把它盖住 这样你就看不见了
I'll mend that for you. I'll cover it up so you won't see it
我知道你和我有同样的感觉
I know you feel the same way as I do
什么意思？
How do you mean?
停下 停下
Stop, stop
我说停下
I said stop!
罗莎
Rosa
马上滚出我的房子
Get out of my house right now
我告诉过你马上出去 否则我会开始尖叫
I told you to get out right now or I'll start screaming
松懈
Take it easy
我要走了
I'm leaving
懦夫
Coward
这是可耻的
It's shameful
懦夫
Coward
真的 这是可耻的
Really, it's shameful
你以为我不知道你在那里吗
Do you think I don't know you're there
看吗？
watching?
你看到了 对吧？
You saw it, right?
我在和你说话
I'm talking to you
看看他会对我做什么？
See what he was going to do to me?
什么也别做
Don't do a thing
呆在那里 都关在里面
Just stay there, all shut in
像虫子一样 像懦夫一样
Like a worm, like a coward
就好像你已经死了一样
It's as if you were dead already!
罗莎求你了 -罗莎 什么？
Rosa, please. - Rosa, what?
每个人都会听到你 -如果他们听到我 我在乎什么？
Everyone will hear you. - What do I care if they hear me?
你不在这里 是吗？
You're not here, are you?
是吗？
Are you?
这里有人吗？
Is there somebody here?
我在问你
I'm asking you
如果你在这里
if you're here
你不在这里
You're not here
我很孤独
I'm all alone
你不是男人 丈夫 父亲 你什么都不是 我一个人
You're not a man, a husband, a father, you're nothing. I'm alone
你是谁？
Who are you?
进去看看你的垃圾小说 关上门
Get in there and read your trashy novels, and shut the door!
父亲
Father?
罗莎 有人在吗？
Rosa! Anyone there?
在这里干吗？请离开
What are you doing here? Please leave
不 让我解释一下
No, let me explain
在过去的几天里 我一直在思考发生了什么
In the last few days I've been thinking a lot about what happened
除了向你道歉
As well as apologising to you,
我想恢复我们的职业关系
I'd like to regain our professional relationship
我认为这有点失控了
I think that this got a little out of hand
我给你带来这件外套要缝 因为袖子撕破了
I brought you this coat to sew, because the sleeves are torn
还有口袋
and the pockets
请放在那里 然后离开
Please put it there and leave
你不想谈谈发生了什么吗？
Don't you want to talk about what happened?
罗莎 够了
Rosa, that's enough
剪刀
The scissors!
抓住他们
Grab them!
在那里
There
我杀了他吗？
Did I kill him?
我想离开
I want to leave
罗莎 求你了 我们不能
Rosa, please, we can't
如果他们找到他 他们会杀了我们
If they find him, they'll kill us
我们必须把他藏起来 除掉他 然后再决定怎么做
We have to hide him and get rid of him, then we'll decide what to do
好吗？
Okay?
别担心
Don't worry
我的床垫着火了
My mattress was on fire
这就是为什么我花了这么长时间
That's why I took so long
我认为这里需要大量的泥土
I think that a lot of dirt is going to be needed here
下午好 罗莎 -你好
Good afternoon, Rosa. - Hello
这位年轻女士正在敲你老房子的门
This young lady was knocking on the door of your old house
我出来告诉她你至少有五年没在那里住了
I came out and told her you hadn't lived there for at least five years
我被给错了地址
I was given the wrong address
这是玛丽·卡门
This is Mari Carmen,
失踪的国民警卫队成员罗德里戈的妻子
the wife of Rodrigo, the civil guard who went missing
我知道
I know
我真的很抱歉
I'm really sorry
我正在参观他过去常去的地方 以防有人知道什么
I'm visiting places he used to go in case somebody knows something
他的同事告诉我他把公司制服带来了
His colleagues told me he brought the company uniforms here
这样你就能修补它们
so that you would mend them
是的 有时他给我带东西
Yes, sometimes he brought me things
谢谢你和我一起去贡萨洛 你真是太好了
Thank you for coming with me Gonzalo. It was very kind of you
你介意我单独和她说话吗？
Would you mind if I spoke to her alone?
不客气 为您服务
Not at all, at your service
好吧 再见
All right, goodbye
我能进来吗？
May I come in?
是的 当然
Yes, of course
我想我帮不了你多少忙
I don't think I'll be able to help you very much
对不起
Sorry
对不起 但是
I'm sorry, but
我知道你也失去了你的丈夫
I know that you lost your husband, too
也许你可以告诉我
Maybe you could tell me
我应该做什么 因为
what I should do, because
我感到失落
I feel lost
放轻松 我去给你拿点水
Take it easy. I'll fetch you some water
这是我丈夫的
This belonged to my husband
你瞧
You see
他留给我修理袖子
He left it for me to mend the sleeve,
但是发生了这么多事情 我忘记了我拥有它
but what with everything that happened, I forgot that I had it
仍然有他的味道
It still smells of him
如果你愿意 我今天晚上可以修理它
If you want, I can mend it this evening
明天给你
And give it to you tomorrow
显然 我不会收费
Obviously, I won't charge
下午
Afternoon
我见到了佛朗哥将军
I saw General Franco
哪里？
Where?
在电影上映前的新闻短片中
In the newsreel they showed before the film
他听起来不像一个领导者
He doesn't sound like a leader
他听起来不像一个领导者？
He doesn't sound like a leader?
他听起来像什么？
So, what does he sound like?
这是什么意思？
What does that mean?
他的声音有点
Well, his voice is sort of
非常温柔 就像
very gentle, like
不太喜欢
Like nothing much
当我们在收音机里听到他时 你说他让你害怕
When we listen to him on the radio you say that he scares you
因为我意识到如果你只听他的 不看他 好吗
Because I've realised that if you only listen to him and don't see him, okay
但是如果你看到他说话 你会说
But if you see him talking, you say
他看起来像一个乔装打扮的女人
He looks like a woman in disguise
上帝 罗莎
God, Rosa
这是真的
It's true
是真的 他看起来不像
It's true, he doesn't look
他的身体和一个
His body doesn't match that of a head of
有些人试图
There are those who have tried to
推测当前的困难
speculate about current difficulties,
好像它们不是其他世代留给我们的东西
as if they were not something other generations bequeathed us
今天的所有困难都源于过去的西班牙
All of today's difficulties stem from the Spain of the past
尽管有这些困难 今天西班牙已经重生
In spite of these difficulties, today Spain has been reborn,
一个沿着
a Spain that is guided along the path of
这是什么？
What's this?
我们在庆祝什么？
What are we celebrating?
我在期待
I'm expecting
我们要有一个孩子了
We're going to have a baby
你确定吗？
Are you sure?
为什么我不能确定？
Why wouldn't I be sure?
罗莎 你确定这是...？-希吉尼奥
Rosa, are you sure that it's...? - Higinio
不 罗莎...-希吉尼奥 请
No, Rosa... - Higinio, please
不 等一下
No, wait a minute
这是我们的孩子 我们要生了 我不想再谈这个了
It's our baby and we're having it. I don't want to talk about it anymore
为什么不呢...？
Why not...?
指国家、国家、军队等 ,
ally - said of a State, country, army, etc.,
为了一个共同的目的而连接到另一个
that is linked to another for a common purpose
亲爱的表哥
Dear cousin,
我希望那里一切都很好 很安静
I hope that things are nice and quiet there
我想你
I miss you
我知道过去几周我们在一起
I know that the last few weeks we spent together
并不容易
were not easy,
但是我们很快就能谈论它
but we'll be able to talk about it soon
我等不及要见到你 给你一个拥抱 我爱你
I can't wait to see you and give you a hug, I love you
你的表弟比阿特丽斯
Your cousin Beatriz
盟军的攻击已经蔓延到了阿登
Allied attacks have spread through the Ardennes
盟军已经占领了巴斯托涅以西的城镇
The Allies have occupied towns to the west of Bastogne
德国军队继续在血腥的战斗中被击败
German troops continue to be overcome in bloody battles
在希腊 丘吉尔敦促无条件投降
In Greece, Churchill has urged the unconditional surrender
来
Coming
好的
OK
这边走
This way
来这里
Come here
如果你知道主人不在这里 你为什么离开她的岗位？
If you know the owner isn't here, why do you leave her post?
你在那里做什么？他们会看到你的
What are you doing there? They'll see you
此时外面没有人
There's no one outside at this time
不要在这里抽烟
And don't smoke here
你真的很蠢 是吧？
You really are stupid, huh?
住口 你有烟味
Stop it, you taste of cigarettes
那么 给我一个拥抱 -你绝望了 不是吗？
Give me a hug, then. - You're desperate, aren't you?
放开我
Get off me
你为什么这么紧张？
Why do you get so uptight?
我不紧张
I don't get uptight
是的 你知道
Yes, you do
就像我不小心碰到你的手
Like when I accidentally brush against your hand
是的 是故意的
Yes, accidentally on purpose
我只是有点谨慎 而你是不负责任的
I'm just a bit cautious, whereas you're irresponsible
告诉我一些事
Tell me something
如果他们向你保证
If they assured you
没人会因为当众吻我而说什么
that no one would say anything for kissing me in public,
你会做吗？
would you do it?
多么愚蠢的问题 啊？
What a stupid question, huh?
回答我
Answer me
回答我 你会吻我吗？
Answer me. Would you kiss me?
我猜 我不知道 我想是的
I guess. I don't know, I guess so
我不这么认为
I don't think so
嘿 别说了
Hey, cut it out
放开
Let go
停止
Cut it out
我会让你放松
I'll make you relax
我会挠你痒痒的
I'll tickle you
我不会让你走的
I won't let you go
糟糕 -等等 等等
Crap. - Wait, wait
没关系
It's okay
把它放在那里
Leave it there
胡说 -妈的
Bollocks. - Shit
它坏了吗？
Is it broken?
别管它 走吧
Leave it. Let's go
上帝啊
Jesus!
去吧 穿好衣服
Go on, get dressed
你会举报我们吗？
Will you report us?
外面的情况怎么样？
How are things on the outside?
什么？-世界大战
What? - The World War
盟军 他们怎么样了？
The Allies. How are they doing?
他们在前进 不是吗？
They're advancing, aren't they?
是的 我是说 他们在前进
Yes, they're advancing, I mean
他们赢了
they're winning
他们在前进？
They're advancing?
我认为这场战争永远不会结束
I think this war is never going to end
这就是我的想法
That's what I think
请不要告诉任何人
Please don't tell anyone
帮我个忙 别说废话
Do me a favour and don't talk rubbish
我为什么要说什么？
Why would I say anything?
我刚刚出现在你们两个面前
I just appeared before you two
但是也不要告诉你的妻子
But don't tell your wife, either
这里没人会说什么 好吗？
No one is going to say anything here, okay?
既然你提到了罗莎
Now that you mentioned Rosa,
直到她回到这里
until she gets back here,
你会一周两次给我带来美味的炖肉
you'll bring me a nice stew twice a week
我能吃下一匹马
I could eat a horse
当你来的时候
And when you come,
在信箱里放一份报纸 任何人都可以
pop a newspaper in the letter box, any one will do
也许我会知道发生了什么
Maybe I'll find out what's going on
好吗？
All right?
好吧 -好吧
All right. - All right
明显
Obviously
犯了错误 否则我们就不会处于这种情况
mistakes were made or else we wouldn't be in this situation
但是在共和党时期做了一些好事
But some good things were done in the Republican period
例如 立法重新分配土地
For example, legislating for land redistribution,
教人们读写 医疗保健
teaching people to read and write, healthcare,
确保每个人都能得到治疗
making sure everyone has access to medical treatment
这是人权问题
It's a human rights matter
这一切都可以实现
That can all be achieved
人们应该有体面的生活
People should have a decent living
你不这样认为吗？
Don't you think so?
我不参与那些事情
I don't get involved in those sort of things
政治和我
Politics and me
没有任何东西
Nothing
这就是该政权所取得的成就
That's what the regime has achieved
确保人们不会思考
Ensuring people don't think
想象你所说的发生了
Imagine that what you say happens,
盟军赢得了战争 他们将佛朗哥赶下台
the Allies win the War and they oust Franco from power
你会怎么做？
What would you do?
熄灭
Go out
在街上庆祝
Out on the street to celebrate
像这样？
Like that?
就这样？
Just like that?
这还不够吗？
Isn't that enough?
继续为我所说的而奋斗
And keep on fighting for what I said
你能告诉每个人我是什么吗？
And will you tell everyone what I am?
我是一个守信的人
I'm a man of my word
但你还是会拉长着脸看着我
But you'd still look at me with a long face
盟军不会改变这一点
The Allies won't change that
或者其他人
Or anyone else
我不能改变的是你脑子里在想什么
What I can't change is what goes on in your head
我认为是我的事
What I think is my business
行
Okay
我告诉你一件事
I'll tell you one thing
你妈妈的鹰嘴豆是我吃过的最好的
Your mother's chickpeas are the best I've ever eaten
周四见？
See you on Thursday?
周四？可能
Thursday? Maybe
如果罗莎还没回来 现在不会太久了
If Rosa hasn't come back yet. It can't be long now
不管怎样 你都可以来
Well, you can come anyway
你将如何向她解释？
And how will you explain it to her?
我不知道
I don't know
以防万一 我会说再见 好吗？再见 伊吉尼奥
Just in case, I'll say goodbye, okay? Bye, Higinio
再见 恩里克
Bye, Enrique
小心你出去的路
Careful on your way out
别担心
Don't worry
伊吉尼奥
Higinio
你好吗？-好吧
How are you? - Fine
你呢？-让我看看
What about you? - Let me take a look
你看起来棒极了
You look great
比我期望的更好找到你
Better than I expected to find you
是个男孩
It's a boy
来这里
Come here
哦 我的小家伙
Oh, my little one
你看到了吗？
Did you see?
打招呼
Say hello
见过他有多小吗？
Seen how little he is?
没那么小 他差不多重5公斤
Not that little, he weighed almost 5kg
医生说他一生中从未见过这样的事情
The doctor said he'd never seen anything like it in his life
我们会有麻烦的
We're going to have a problem
他看起来和你一样
He looks just like you
什么事？
Yes?
你知道他们会在村子里说什么吗？
You know what they'll say in the village?
就像我一样
Just like me
是的 现在
Yes, for now
他还不认识你
He doesn't know you yet
那里 那里 亲爱的
There, there, sweetie
今天标志着盟军在欧洲的胜利
Today marks the Allied victory in Europe
德国已经无条件投降
Germany has surrendered unconditionally
欧洲的战争结束了
War is over in Europe
投降仪式于凌晨2点41分在兰斯签署
The surrender was signed in Reims at 2.41am
联合通讯社
The United Press agency
宣布德国外交部长冯·克罗西克
announces that the German foreign minister, von Krosigk,
弗伦斯堡的广播
broadcasting from Flensburg,
声明最高统帅部接受无条件投降
states that the high command accepts unconditional surrender
该机构补充说 官方的胜利宣言
The same agency adds that the official declaration of victory
将在下午6点制作
will be made at 6pm
这将会结束
This is going to end
我们可以出去了 -他正要睡觉
We'll be able to go outside. - He was just going to sleep
没关系 我们要庆祝
It doesn't matter, we have to celebrate
我会给你你应得的生活
that I'm going to give you the life you deserve
现在 詹姆 杰米
Right now, Jaime. Jaime
把他给我 -现在 现在
Give him to me. - Right now, right now
和爸爸一起 现在爸爸在街上
With Daddy. Right now with Daddy on the street
詹姆
Jaime!
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
去散步 来吗？
Going to the promenade, coming?
安东尼奥能和我们一起去吗？
Can Antonio come with us?
我们有很多人
There are a lot of us
只是看看 然后
Just to look, then
行
Okay
走吧
Let's go
十年-十年的时期
decade - period of ten years
又来了？帮我个忙 把事情了结 我以前告诉过你
Again? Do me a favour and close things. I've told you before
好了
Done
西班牙已经加入了联合国
Spain has joined the UN
那是什么？
What's that?
联合起来和平解决问题的一组国家
A group of nations that joined together to solve things peacefully
他们知道佛朗哥在这里做什么吗？
Do they know what Franco is doing here?
不知道 但是现在我们是联合国的一员了
No idea. But now we're a member of the UN
小心 这很热
Watch out, this is hot
詹姆 今天早上和你在一起的那个孩子是谁？
Who's that kid you were with this morning, Jaime?
拉法
Rafa
你去哪了？
Where did you go?
踢足球
To play football
去那个我告诉过你适合玩耍的荒地？
To that waste ground where I told you it was good for playing?
谁玩的？
And who played?
很多你不认识的孩子
Lots of kids you don't know
如果你告诉我他们是谁 我会的
If you tell me who they are I will
我不知道他们的名字
I don't know their names
嗯 你必须给他们起个名字
Well, you must call them something
汤姆 迪克 哈利 把球递给我 好吗？
Tom, Dick, Harry, pass me the ball, right?
我们不太在意名字
We're not much bothered about names
我说:嘿 传球 就这样
I say: hey, pass it! That's it
坐进去 等等 等等
Sit in. Hang on, wait
就这样
That's it
这边请
There you go
这里
Here
村子里发生了什么事？
What's going on in the village?
生活 伊吉尼奥 我不知道
Life, Higinio, I don't know
一定发生了什么事 嗯？
Something must be going on, huh?
他们昨天撞倒了普鲁登的狗
They ran over Pruden's dog yesterday
邮差恩里克要结婚了
Enrique the postman is getting married
他要结婚了？
He's getting married?
每个人都认为他会保持单身 但不 他要结婚了
Everyone thought he'd stay a bachelor, but no, he's marrying
请停下来 詹姆 我不能集中精神
Stop that please, Jaime, I can't concentrate
你为什么穿女人的羊毛衫？
Why are you wearing a woman's cardigan?
你不喜欢吗？
Don't you like it?
我不知道
I don't know
你知道你要做什么 -什么？
You know what you have to do. - What?
成长
Grow up
行
Okay
我去拿
I'll get it
闭嘴
Shut that
闭嘴 好吗？
Shut it, will you?
你阿姨在吗？
Is your aunt there?
不 她出去了
No, she went out
这条裤子需要缝补
These trousers need mending
你可以把它们留在这里 我会记下来的 进来
You can leave them here, I'll make a note. Come in
你叫什么名字？你需要什么？
What's your name? What do you need?
你不觉得这有点年轻吗？
Aren't you a bit young for this?
不知道 我已经做过一千次了
Dunno. I've done it a thousand times
是吗？
Yeah?
好吧 写下来
All right, write this down
就这样
That's it
我叫贡萨洛·帕拉西奥
My name is Gonzalo Palacio
好吧 -看
Okay. - Look
拉链需要修理 看
The zip needs fixing, look
它需要改变 我不知道
It needs changing, I don't know
然后 这个洞 看
And then, this hole here. Look
好吗？
Okay?
怎么了？
So, what's up?
你是家里的男人 对吗？
You're the man of the house, right?
是
Yeah
你阿姨对你好吗？
Is your aunt good to you?
你知道你叔叔和婶婶是我的邻居吗？
You know that your aunt and uncle were neighbors of mine?
他们对我很严厉
They were tough on me
你想念他们吗？
And do you miss them?
谁？
Who?
你认为是谁？你妈妈和爸爸
Who do you think? Your mum and dad
是的 是的 当然
Yeah. Yeah, of course
怎么了？
What's up?
你不确定吗？
Are you unsure?
不
No
我不是不确定
I'm not unsure
你不记得了 你还小 是吗？
You wouldn't remember, you were little, weren't you?
那只猫有你的舌头吗？
Has the cat got your tongue?
我不咬人 小伙子
I don't bite, lad
你好 贡萨洛
Hello, Gonzalo
下午好 -怎么了？
Afternoon. - What's up?
我带了这条裤子给你补 他正在记笔记
I brought these trousers for you to mend and he was taking note
让我们看看
Let's have a look
好吧 那么
Okay, then
我将在两天内准备好这个
I'll have this ready in two days
两天后？-你可以捡起来
In two days? - You can pick it up
我妻子可能会来
My wife might come by
好吧 那再见 -好吧 再见 小伙子
All right. Bye, then. - Okay. Bye, lad
再见
Bye
再见 罗莎 -再见
Bye, Rosa. - Bye
他在这里做什么？为什么出乎意料？
What's he doing here? Why out of the blue?
不知道 -你没看见他在附近吗？
No idea. - Don't you see him around?
有时候 -多久一次？
Sometimes. - How often?
这个村庄没那么大
The village isn't that big
让我们考虑一下
Let's think about it
他一定说了什么 暗示了什么
He must have said something, hinted at something
他带着裤子来了
He came with the trousers
他来是为了让你能修补它们和其他东西 是吗？
He came so you could mend them and something else, huh?
我跟你说了什么？
And what did I tell you?
我们排练了多少次了？
How many times have we rehearsed it?
我不会和陌生人说话 我不会和陌生人说话
I won't talk to strangers, I won't talk to strangers
一切都是徒劳
All for nothing
对不起
Sorry
不 他们会杀了我的
No, they'll kill me!
聪明点 他们会杀了我的 -够了
Wise up, they'll kill me! - That's enough
聪明点 这不是游戏
Wise up, this isn't a game
别理他 孩子 -对不起
Pay him no heed, son. - I'm sorry
分离-孤立 遥远 遥远
separate - isolated, distant, remote
孩子们将会有一场真正的盛宴
The kids will have a real feast
我们都准备好了吗？詹姆
Are we all ready? Jaime!
詹姆
Jaime!
快点 亲爱的
Hurry up, love
抱歉抱歉 -大家都在等着
Sorry, sorry. - Everyone is waiting
曼纽尔 我们不是模特 -你们能交换一下吗？
Manuel, we're not models. - Can you two swap?
把手放在你妈妈的肩膀上
Put your hands on your mum's shoulders
好吧 等一下
All right, just a second
准备好了吗？-对
All ready, okay? - Right
我们准备好了
We're ready
站住 嗯？
Stand still, huh?
美国军乐队演奏《欢迎参军》
The American military band plays Welcome to the Army.
他们问候艾森豪威尔
They greet Eisenhower
在人群欢呼的背景下
against a backdrop of cheers from the crowds here,
当他下飞机的时候
while he gets off the plane
阁下在飞机的底部
His Excellency is at the foot of the plane,
现在两位国家元首
and now both heads of state,
艾森豪威尔总统和佛朗哥相互热情问候
President Eisenhower and Franco, greet each other warmly
弗朗哥之后是航空部长和外交部长
Franco is followed by the ministers of Aviation and Foreign Affairs
西班牙驻华盛顿大使和美国驻马德里大使
the Spanish ambassadors in Washington and the USA in Madrid,
和维拉维德的侯爵夫人
and the Marquises of Villaverde
注意 美国总统要讲话了
Attention, the US president is going to speak
什么？
What?
那件衣服真的很适合你
That dress really suits you
谢谢你
Thank you
不要改变
Don't change
当然
Sure
我喜欢看到你看起来很漂亮
I like to see you looking pretty
别傻了
Don't be silly
教区的人们正在组织旅行
The parish people are organising trips
任何人都可以报名
Anyone can sign up
很好
Fine
小伙子的一些朋友和他们的父母一起去
Some of the lad's friends go with their parents
我在想也许我也可以和詹姆一起去
I was thinking that maybe I could go with Jaime, too
哪里？
Where?
下一次旅行是去马贝拉
The next trip is to Marbella
去海滩
To the beach
但那不是我们的蜜月吗？
But wasn't that for our honeymoon?
如果最后没有呢？
What if there isn't one in the end?
为什么不会有？
Why wouldn't there be?
另外 如果我出了什么事
Besides, if something happens to me
如果我生病或发生了什么事 谁会来？
If I fall ill or something happens, who will come?
我认为这很愚蠢 罗莎
I think it's stupid, Rosa
你一个人在这里做什么？来吧 你还有时间
What will you do here by yourself? Come on, you still have time
我希望我能 普里 我有一堆工作要做
I wish I could, Puri. I have a stack of work
我不能
I can't
规矩点 嗯？
And behave yourself, huh?
是的 别担心 阿姨
Yes, don't worry, Auntie
我能拿我的手提包吗？
Can I have my handbag?
请问这是谁的电话号码？
Whose phone number is this, please?
一定是顾客的 我不记得了
Must be a customer's, I don't remember
你什么时候开始抽烟了？
Since when do you smoke?
我不知道
I don't
你为什么在这里翻找？-弄清楚你对我隐瞒了什么
Why are you rummaging here? - Figuring out what you keep from me
正是我所需要的
Just what I needed
你什么时候开始和国民警卫队的妻子混在一起了？
Since when do you mix with the civil guard's wife?
哪个国民警卫队？
Which civil guard?
你可以躺在那里 而不是在家
You can lie out there, not here at home
你什么时候开始和她混在一起了？
Since when do you mix with her?
我不知道在哪里...-我看见你了
I don't know where... - I saw you
别大惊小怪的 好吗？
Don't kick up a fuss, okay?
和她交往了15年 你却不告诉我？
Fifteen years hanging out with her and you're not going to tell me?
不是十五年 事情不会一夜之间发生
Not fifteen years, things don't happen overnight
看在上帝的份上 罗莎
For God's sake, Rosa
看在上帝份上
For God's sake
你知道你在做什么吗？
Do you realise what you're doing?
你正在危及一切
You're jeopardising everything
我该怎么办？-为什么是她？
What should I do? - Why her?
解释什么...-你解释
Explain what... - You explain
如果她在街上拦住我想聊天 怎么办？
If she stops me on the street and wants to chat, what?
我说不吗？-这会减轻你的良心吗？
Do I say no? - Does it ease your conscience?
我是睡在尸体上的人
I'm the one who sleeps on top of the dead body
拜托 罗莎
Please, Rosa
你为什么不出去？
Why don't you go outside?
你可以做你自己
You can be yourself
出去吧 -什么？
Go on out. - What?
这里有一个罗莎 外面还有一个
There's one Rosa here and another out there
你是个骗子 我不认识你
You're an impostor. I don't know you
当然不
Of course not
我能怎么做呢？
What can I do?
呆在这里？和你一起爬进去 没有生活？
Stay here? Crawl in there with you, not have a life?
我是你丈夫
I'm your husband
我受够了 希吉尼奥 -什么？
I'm sick of it, Higinio. - Of what?
你讨厌什么？-什么？
What are you sick of? - What?
被关起来？那是我
Of being cooped up? That's me
厌倦了这样的生活 我受不了了
Sick of living this way, I can't take it
厌倦了对街上的每个人撒谎
Sick of lying to everyone on the street
我呢？我看不到阳光 关了二十年
And me? I don't see the light of day. Twenty years cooped up
我的一生都是你和一个可能不属于我的孩子
My whole life is you and a kid who might not be mine
再说一遍
Say that again
这是你的主意
It was your idea
这是你的主意 你的主意
It was your idea, your idea
你对我说...-重复你刚才说的话
You said to me... - Repeat what you just said
你说我儿子的事 -你说 呆在那里
What you said about my son. - You said, stay in there
你把我关了20年
You locked me up for 20 years
有一个快速的解决方案
There's a quick solution
被锁在那个破洞里
Locked up in that shitty hole
那我来为你开门
I'll open the door for you, then
住手 -不 出去
Stop it. - No, get out
走吧 我再也受不了你了 -罗莎
Go, I can't stand you anymore! - Rosa
我再也受不了你了
I can't stand you anymore
你甚至不能出去
You're not even capable of going out
你做不到 那是你的问题
You can't do it, that's your problem
好 好 好
Well, well, well
我们这么做是为了能在一起 对吗？
We did all of this so we could be together, right?
看看我们在一起有多好
Well look how together we are
你弄坏了我的东西
You've broken my things
你什么时候到的？
When did you arrive?
昨晚
Last night
他迟到了 这就是为什么我没有告诉你
He got in late. That's why I didn't tell you
他告诉我大海是什么样的
He told me what the sea is like
告诉你爸爸 -是的
Tell your dad. - Yeah
我告诉她它是咸的
I was telling her that it's salty
但不像你在里面放了盐
But not like you've added salt to it
一个波浪打在我的脸上
A wave hit me in the face,
它闻起来像新鲜的鱼或者类似的东西
and it smelled like fresh fish or something like that
温度会变化
And the temperature changes
突然 你感觉到一股寒流围绕着你的双腿
Suddenly you feel a cold current around your legs
你呆在同一个地方 但还有另一层温暖
You stay in the same place, but there's another warm layer
听起来不错
Sounds nice
海底很奇怪 就像陆地一样 但是
And the seabed is strange, it's like the land but
全是沙子
it's all sand
它是什么颜色的？
What colour is it?
深蓝
Dark blue
在其他地方它看起来是绿色的
And it looks greenish in other places
好像它在动 蓝色是
As if it were moving. The blue is
混入
mixed in with
用白色
with white
改变——改变外貌、状况或行为
to change - to modify appearance, condition or behaviour
西班牙——400亿英镑的收入阳光繁荣
SPAIN - 40 BILLION IN REVENUE SUNSHINE BOOM
乐观地面对1963年
FACING 1963 WITH OPTIMISM
今天 像昨天一样
Today, like yesterday
亲爱的听众
Dear listeners
出来一会儿 你被关了一整天
Come out for a bit. You've been cooped up all day
我在这里很好
I'm fine here
想要点什么吗？
Want something?
嗨 我和一个朋友在这里
Hi. I'm here with a friend
在这里等我
Wait for me here
嗨 -嗨 妈妈
Hi. - Hi, Mum
过来 胡安
Come here, Juan
爸爸 不用担心 胡安知道你在这里
Dad, no need to worry, Juan knows you're here
对不起 我之前不能让你知道 但是他有麻烦 需要帮助
Sorry I couldn't let you know before, but he's in a fix and needs help
罗莎 我妈妈
Rosa, my mum
见到你很高兴
Pleased to meet you
25年来一直保守着我在这里的秘密
Twenty-five years keeping it a secret that I'm here,
现在因为你认为事情正在改变
and now because you think things are changing,
你告诉一个朋友你爸爸藏在这里？
you tell a friend your dad is hiding here?
只是几天而已
It's only for a couple of days
你不能表现出一些团结吗？
Can't you show some solidarity?
你的战斗精神呢？
What about your fighting spirit?
他们在塞戈维亚找到了一个躲了20年的人
They found a guy in Segovia, 20 years in hiding
他们得到了线报
They got a tip-off
他们说马德里没有一个特别的小组来寻找你的同类
They say Madrid has not a special group to find your kind
当局查明是否有当地的密报或线索
The authorities find out if there are local tip-offs or clues
马德里没有具体的搜索行动
There's no specific search operation organised from Madrid
你就像一个老师
You're like a teacher
谢谢
Thanks
这不是恭维
It's not a compliment
什么事？
Yes?
她说我越来越执迷不悟 不肯给我信息
She says I'm getting obsessive, won't give me information
他们警告过你吗？
Did they warn you?
没有 只是轻声说
No, just said speak softly
你说你看到了另一个人的藏身之处
You said you saw the other guy's hiding place
是的 但是当他不在的时候
Yeah, but when he wasn't there
给我细节
Give me details
他是一个在前线战斗的无政府主义者
He was an anarchist who fought on the front
不 我是说藏身之处
No, I mean the hiding place
在一段楼梯下
Under a flight of stairs
他建了一堵墙来盖住那个洞
He built a wall to cover the hole
如果这是在楼梯下面
If this was under the stairs
这家伙建了一堵墙来盖住这个洞
the guy built a wall to cover the hole
你只能站在一个地方
You could only stand up in one place,
那是在这里
that was here
这真的不是很安全
It wasn't really very safe
他在哪里做生意？
Where did he do his business?
他怎么拉屎的？
How did he crap?
楼上的排水管穿过了那个洞
The upstairs drainpipe went through the hole
他在管子上打了一个洞 在那里做生意
He made a hole in the pipe, did his business there
我把它放在桶里 然后放在外面
I do it in a bucket and then put it outside
正确
Right
你可以告诉其他人我的事
You can tell that other guy about me,
但是请不要提到我的名字
but please don't mention my name
好
All right
知道还有其他人处于类似的情况会让他们精神振奋
Knowing there are others in a similar situation will raise their spirits
让他们觉得有人陪伴
Makes them feel accompanied
陪同 他说
Accompanied, he says
这里唯一的公司是令人毛骨悚然的爬虫
The only company here are the creepy crawlies,
一些零碎的东西
the few bits and bobs,
和死亡 这就是所有的公司
and death. That's all the company
别这么说
Don't say that
至少你可以和他们在一起
At least you could be with them
你在开玩笑
You're joking
他们现在在哪里？看看他们 在外面
Where are they now? Look at them, out there
我在这里
And here I am inside
詹姆已经长大了 我甚至没有注意到
Jaime has grown up and I didn't even notice
胡安
Juan,
听我说
listen to me
忘记传单和秘密会议
Forget leaflets and secret meetings
出去散步 带上一个女人
Go out and take a walk with a woman on your arm
生孩子 和他们在户外玩耍
And have kids, play with them outdoors,
像父亲应该做的那样
like a father should
听听孩子们的笑声
Listen to the kids laugh
不要像我一样坐在这里缝纫
Not sit in here sewing like me
我将继续缝纫
I'll carry on sewing
罗莎给我的命令
This order Rosa gave me
是前天的
is for the day before yesterday
弗朗哥·弗兰克用西班牙语简单、真诚、直白
franco frank in Spanish simple, sincere, straightforward
态度诚实
and honest in attitude
通常 在年底
Often, at the end of the year,
当我们聚集在家里进行精神反思时
when we gather at home and engage in spiritual reflection
在上帝的和平中
in the peace of God
也许买电视不是个好主意
Maybe it wasn't a good idea to buy the TV
幸福不仅仅取决于它的顺利进展
wellbeing does not merely depend on its smooth progress
我们付了一大笔钱...-罗莎 拜托
We're paying a fortune... - Rosa, please
我听不见
I can't hear
西班牙又一次
Spain is once again
你会相信吗 爸爸？
Would you credit it, Dad?
因为他藏在洞里30年了 看看你
Hidden in a hole for 30 years because of him and look at you
什么？
What?
二十六年的和平
Twenty-six years of peace
算了吧
Forget it
在这个世界上 我们因共同的理想而团结一致
in which we have lived united by a common ideal,
坚持不懈地坚持正义的目标
upholding our goals of justice with tireless perseverance
晚餐准备好了 伊吉尼奥
Dinner's served. Higinio
当我们周围的人
while all around us
一个有问题的世界
a problematic world caused
麻烦 戏剧性的变化
troubles, dramatic changes
请自便 儿子
Help yourself, son
挖出：1  从地下挖出
to dig up 1. Exhume, remove from under the earth
2 找回尘封的记忆
2. Bring back the memory of what is forgotten and buried in silence
在这里 我找不到
Here it is, I couldn't find it
如果你买了一台电视 你一定会过得很好
If you bought a TV, things must be going well for you
那是笑声
That's a laugh
我已经付了三年的钱了
I've been paying it off for three years
我欠你什么？
What do I owe you?
那将是
That'll be
三十五比塞塔
Thirty-five pesetas
天哪
Jesus
数到三十
Make it thirty
前几天我在你的老房子里
I was in your old house the other day
真的吗？-是的
Really? - Yes
一对夫妇搬进来了
A married couple moved in
玛丽亚·Á·安赫尔斯不在吗？-没有
Is María Ángeles not there? - No
她母亲生病了 她离开了 她不会付两次房租
Her mother fell ill and she left. She isn't going to pay two rents
所以她离开了
So she left
我去跟这对夫妇打招呼 他们说 请进
I went to say hello to the couple and they said, Please come in.
你知道厨房里有个洞吗？他说
Did you know there was a hole in the kitchen? he says
一个洞？
A hole?
一个大的
A big one
罐子在哪里 -对
Where the jars are. - Right
架子的整个长度
The whole length of the shelf
一个人可以毫无困难地融入其中
A person could fit in there no trouble
我第一次听说它 你的零钱
First I heard of it. Your change
里面甚至还有一条旧毯子
There was even an old blanket inside
一定是玛丽亚·Á·安赫尔斯的 -没有
Must have belonged to María Ángeles. - No
我去见了她母亲
I went to see her mother,
我问她
and I asked her
她说她对此一无所知
She said she knew nothing about it
我从我叔叔那里继承了那栋房子 然后卖掉了
I inherited that house from my uncle, then I sold it,
我不知道那里有什么
I don't know what was there or anything
当然
Sure
一定是你叔叔的
Must have been your uncle's
是的 可能吧 -当然
Yes, probably. - Sure
好了 再见 -好吧 罗莎
Okay, bye now. - Okay, Rosa
坚持下去
Hang on
一定要小心...-不要绊倒
Must be careful... - Don't trip
随着脚步 行
with the step. Okay
那再见 -再见
Bye then. - Bye
他又来了
He's there again
他不会放弃 直到抓住我
He won't give up till he catches me
哪里？
Where?
在那边 在酒吧
Over there, at the bar
因为他觉得无聊
Because he gets bored
自从他妻子去世后 他变得很无聊
Since his wife died he gets bored
他已经在那里呆了两周了
He's been there two weeks
你也可以不盯着窗外
You could stop staring out the window, too
为什么现在要做这些？
Why do all this now?
他知道整个故事
He knows the whole story
他很着迷
He's obsessed
上帝
God
烧了它
Burn that
你必须一点一点地把它拿出来
You'll have to take it out bit by bit
如果你同时做所有的事情
If you do it all at once
哦 亲爱的上帝
Oh, dear Lord
不要把这件事告诉那个小伙子
Don't tell the lad about this
是我
It's me
晚上
Evening
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
请不要走 不要把我一个人留在这里
Please don't go. Don't leave me here alone
贡萨洛不在广场上 小伙子很快就会到了 我不会太久的
Gonzalo isn't in the square, the lad will be here soon. I won't be long
别担心 -罗莎 拜托
Don't worry. - Rosa, please
我马上回来
I'll be right back
他妈的混蛋
Fucking bastard
好了 我抓住你了
There, I've got you
进你的小洞里
Get in your little hole
我知道你在那里
I know you're there
我看见你了
I saw you
伊吉尼奥
Higinio!
你在里面
You're in there
你在那里 你这个混蛋
You're there, you bastard
开门 开门
Open up! Open up!
你是谁？在这里干吗？
Who are you? What are you doing here?
什么意思?
What do you mean?
滚出去
Get out!
我看见他了 我知道他藏在那里 -出去
I saw him. I know he's hiding over there. - Out!
我会告诉所有人的 -出去 马上离开这里
I'll tell everyone! - Out! Out of here right now!
马上出去
Get out right now!
要打一个老人吗？
Gonna hit an old man?
你真可耻 -现在滚出我的房子
Shame on you! - Out of my house now!
你应该感到羞耻 -现在出去
You should be ashamed! - Get out now!
他藏在那里
He's hiding in there
我都看到了 -发生什么事了？
I saw it all. - What's going on?
发生什么事了？-你在这里也无妨
What is happening? - Just as well you're here
他们把战犯伊吉尼奥·布兰科藏在这里
They're hiding Higinio Blanco here, a war criminal
那是谎言 -他今年被判刑了
That's a lie. - He was sentenced in the year
你说我是骗子？-请冷静
You're calling me a liar? - Please calm down
我们是为了一扇破门而来的
We're here about a broken door
谁住在这里？-我
Who lives here? - Me
我刚到家
I just arrived home
我发现他完全喝醉了 在我家
I found him completely drunk and in my house,
我不知道他来这里偷什么
I don't know what he came here to steal
后门被打碎了
The back door is splintered
你能看见吗？
Can you see it?
是你做的吗？-坚持住
Did you do that? - Hang on
我不是小偷 我不是来偷东西的
I'm no thief, I didn't come here to steal
我告诉你一个战犯藏在这里:伊吉尼奥·布兰科
I'm telling you that a war criminal is hiding here: Higinio Blanco
你强行进入了吗？-当然是他
Did you force entry? - Of course it was him
我哥哥因为他而死
My brother died because of him
你破门而入了吗？
Did you break down the door and trespass?
但这是什么？
But what is this?
请进去看看我在跟你说什么
Please go in and take a look at what I'm telling you about
你喝酒了吗？
Have you been drinking?
你没看见他有酒精的味道吗？
Can't you see he stinks of alcohol?
你必须到车站来 -看看
You'll have to come to the station. - Take a look
你为什么不照我说的做？-我在这里下命令
Why don't you do what I say? - I give the orders here!
你们两个 马上去车站
Both of you, down to the station now!
两者都有？我把我知道的都告诉你了 -我什么也没做
Both? I told you all I know. - I didn't do anything
你应该看看里面
You should look in there
你好吗 儿子？
How are you, son?
我很好 爸爸在哪？-在这里
I'm fine. Where's Dad? - In here
进来
Come in
结束了
It's over
晚上
Evening
他们陪你了吗？
Did they accompany you?
不 他们也不会
No, and they won't, either
发生什么事了？-他们让他为门付钱
What happened? - They made him pay for the door
并支付赔偿金
And pay compensation, too
好的
Good
他在车站说了什么？
What did he say at the station?
你怎么想呢?
What do you think?
任何古老的谎言 我不知道
Any old lie, I don't know
他说你是个告密者
He said you were an informer
你举报了邻居
You reported neighbors
你举报了他的兄弟 所以他们会杀了他
You reported his brother so they'd kill him
这都是真的吗？
Is that all true?
这是真的还是假的？
Is it true or not?
我们这些失踪的人被指责犯有所有的战争罪
Those of us who disappeared were blamed for all the war crimes
这是事实
That's the truth
我受够了
I'm sick of this
如果我必须保护你 我有权知道你是谁
If I have to protect you, I deserve to know who you are
你做了什么
and what you've done
如果你什么都没做 你在那里呆了30年是不正常的
It's not normal that you've been there 30 years if you didn't do anything
杰米...-不要再从这个开始了
Jaime... - Don't start with this again
你吓了我一辈子 我受够了
You've been scaring me all my life, I'm done
我从小就害怕
I've been terrified since I was a kid,
测量每个手势 看 对每个人撒谎
measuring every gesture, look, lying to everyone,
说我妈妈是我阿姨 我不认识我爸爸
saying my mother is my aunt and I don't know my father,
事实上他住在我房子的墙后
when in fact he lived behind a wall in my house,
像这样躲在那里
hiding there like
你不觉得羞耻吗？这是我的房子
Aren't you ashamed? This is my house
你的房子？
Your house?
什么房子？不在这里
What house? Not here
那是你的房子 你住在那里
That's your house, you live there
懦夫躲起来 而其他人在前线战斗并死去
Cowards who hid away while the others fought and died on the front
在我们继续生活的时候 我不得不躲在墙后
have to live behind a wall while our lives go on
请小声点 -谁在听？
Lower your voice, please. - Who's listening?
邻居？-他们能听到你
The neighbors? - They can hear you
他们从一开始就知道他在那里
They've known he's there from the beginning
路易莎告诉我她听到他在睡梦中大喊大叫
Luisa told me she hears him shouting in his sleep
那不是真的 -想象他的梦
That's not true. - Imagine his dreams
她的父母认为他被关了这么久已经疯了
Her parents think he's gone mad from being locked up so long
隐藏得像
Hidden like a
总是谈论战斗
Always talking about fighting
你的战斗方式毫无意义
Your way of fighting meant nothing
一个没有勇气出去的懦夫
A coward who doesn't have the balls to go outside
不要那样和你父亲说话
Don't talk to your father that way
你不知道我们为你经历了什么
You've no idea what we've gone through for you
我同情你们两个
I pity you two
外面没人等着吃你活着
There's no one out there waiting to eat you alive
我在警察局
I was at the police station
甚至国民警卫队也不感兴趣
Even the civil guard aren't interested
伊吉尼奥 -什么？
Higinio. - What?
你认为这个小伙子是对的吗？
Do you think the lad is right?
关于什么？
About what?
如果你出来 什么都不会发生
That if you came out, nothing would happen
决不
No way
待在这里是一回事
Being in here is one thing,
他们让我住在那里是另一回事
them letting me live out there is another
晚安 -晚安
Good night. - Good night
谁在那里？
Who's there?
慢慢地挖掘我 嗯？
Took your time digging me up, huh?
请把烟咽下去 它有气味
Please swallow the smoke, it smells
真的很干
It's really dry
干燥的...你见过自己吗？
Dry... Have you seen yourself?
你肯定是干的
You sure are dry
没错
That's true
你真的很勇敢 伊吉尼奥
You're really brave, Higinio
勇敢到连自己的生命都不要去拿
Brave enough not even to take your own life
我想你已经听腻了
I guess you're sick of hearing it,
但是很少有人会容忍你的正直
but few people would put up with this with your integrity
谢谢
Thanks
也许你的恐惧不会让人们把你视为英雄
Maybe your fear won't make people see you as a hero
但是你也因此成为了受害者
But you're no less a victim because of it
谢谢
Thanks
哦 伊吉尼奥
Oh, Higinio
大赦——对被判犯有政治罪的人的官方赦免
amnesty - official pardon for those convicted of political offences
这是新闻
Here is the news
纪念内战结束30周年
Commemorating the 30th anniversary of the end of the Civil War
以及全国的和平
and peace nationwide,
部长会议宣布了一项法令
the Council of Ministers has announced a Decree
下令终止与战争有关的任何事件引起的犯罪
ordering the expiration of offences deriving from any event related to the war
该法令的序言指出
The preamble of the Decree states that
这是一场自相残杀的斗争 所有的结果都不起作用
all the consequences of what was a fratricidal struggle, are inoperative
1939年4月1日之前犯下的所有罪行
All crimes committed prior to 1 April 1939
将从1969年4月1日起失去时效
will be time-barred as from 1 April 1969
案件将被驳回并结案
Cases will be dismissed and closed
罗莎
Rosa
大赦已经宣布
Amnesty has been declared
别动
Hold it there
趴下 趴下
Down, down
放在床上
Put it on the bed
不 这是床单
No, this is bed linen
我们出去的第一件事就是
The first thing we'll do when we go out
就是给你买新衣服 让你看起来更聪明
is buy you new clothes so you look smart
让我们看看如何
Let's see how
它不合适 对吗？
It doesn't fit, right?
我去拿些剪刀 马上修好
I'll fetch some scissors and fix it right away
现在把我们的衣服挂在一起并不危险
Now it's not dangerous to hang out our clothes together
伊吉尼奥
Higinio
你为什么脱掉裤子？
Why did you take off the trousers?
我不知道 罗莎 -你什么意思？
I don't know, Rosa. - What do you mean?
如果一个邻居在追你 马德里人会怎么说并不重要
What they say in Madrid doesn't matter if a neighbor is after you
什么邻居？
What neighbor?
你没听到他们在广播和报纸上说什么吗？
Didn't you hear what they're saying on the radio and in the press?
这里没那么糟
It's not that bad here
开始
Come on
好吧 那么
All right, then
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
你没看见吗？
Can't you see?
你要去哪里？
Where are you going?
我要走了
I'm going
去海边
to the coast
去海边 那是我要去的地方
To the seaside, that's where I'm going
你怎么去那里？
How will you get there?
住手 -巴士11点出发
Stop that. - The bus leaves at 11
我为什么知道？
Why do I know that?
因为我每周都看时间表
Because I look at the timetables every week
如果你愿意 跟我来
So if you want, come with me
到了那里我会给你买泳裤
and I'll buy you a swim trunks when we get there
你知道我不能去
You know I can't go
别胡说了 罗莎
Stop this nonsense. Rosa!
罗莎
Rosa!
拜托 罗莎
Please, Rosa
不要再离开
Don't leave again
罗莎
Rosa!
出去离开一个地方到外面去
to go out to leave a place and go outside
你好
Hello
罗莎
Rosa
你没赶上公共汽车吗？
Didn't you catch the bus?
看起来是这样
Looks that way
我必须拿到我的身份证
I have to get my ID card
你好
Hello
我能帮你什么吗？
Can I help you?
原来我们以前住在这里
It turns out we used to live here
至少30年前
at least 30 years ago
嗯 这房子确实是
Well, this house was
自1969年该法令公布以来 越来越多的案件被揭露
From the publication of the Decree in 1969, more and more cases were revealed of people
人们因害怕报复 躲在家里
who, fearing reprisals, went into hiding at home
这些人被赋予了“鼹鼠”的绰号
These people were given the nickname moles
在某些情况下 他们躲藏了30多年
In some cases, they remained in hiding for over 30 years